Hi, my name is John. I lead the search and
machine learning teams at Google.
I think it's amazingly inspiring that people all
over the world
turn to search engines to ask
trivial questions and incredibly
important questions, so it's a huge responsibility to give them the best answers that we can.
Hi, my name is
Akshaya and I work on the Bing search team.
There are many times where we'll
start looking into artificial
intelligence and machine learning, but we
have to address how are the users going
to use this because end of the day we
want to make an impact to society.
Let's ask a simple question.
"How long does it take to travel to Mars?"
Where did these results come from and
why was this listed before the other one?
Okay, let's dive in and see how the
search engine turned your request into a result.
The first thing you need to know
is when you do a search, the search
engine isn't actually going out to the
World Wide Web to run your search in real time.
That's because there's
over a billion websites on the internet
and hundreds more being created every
single minute, so if the search engine
had to look through every single site to
find the one you wanted, it would just take forever.
So to make your search faster,
search engines are constantly scanning
the web in advance to record the
information that might help with your search later.
That way when you search
about "travel to Mars" the search engine
already has what it needs to give you an
answer in real time.
Here's how it works:
The internet is a web of pages connected
to each other by hyperlinks.
Search engines are constantly running a program
called "spider" that crawls through
these web pages to collect information
about them.
Each time it finds a hyperlink, it follows it until it has
visited every page it can find on the entire internet.
For each page of the
spider visits, it records any information
it might need for a search by adding it to
a special database called a search index.
Now, let's go back to that search from
earlier and see if we can figure out how
the search engine came up with the results.
When you ask "how long does it take to travel to Mars", the search engine looks each of those words in the
search index to immediately get a list of all
the pages on the internet containing
those words, but just looking for these
search terms could return millions of
pages so the search engine needs to be
able to determine the best matches to show you first.
This is where it gets tricky because the search engine may need to guess what you're looking for.
Each search engine uses its own algorithm to rank the pages based on what it thinks you want.
The search engine's ranking algorithm might check if
your search term shows up in the page title,
it might check if all of the words
show up next to each other, or any number
of other calculations that helped it better determine which pages you'll want to see and which you won't.
Google invented
the most famous algorithm for choosing
the most relevant results for a search, by taking into account how many other web pages link to a given page.
The idea is that if lots of websites think that a
web page is interesting, then it's
probably the one you're looking for.
This algorithm was called "Page Rank", not because it ranks web pages, but because
it was named after its inventor, Larry
Page, who is one of the founders of Google.
Because the website often makes money
when you visit it, spammers are constantly
trying to find ways to game the search algorithm so that their pages are listed higher in the results.
Search engines
regularly update their algorithms to
prevent fake or untrustworthy sites from
reaching the top.
Ultimately, it's up to you to keep an eye out for these
pages that are untrustworthy by looking
at the web address and making sure it's
a reliable source.
Search programs are always evolving to
improve the algorithms so the return better results, faster results then their competitors.
Today's search engines even use
information that you haven't explicitly provided to help you narrow down your search.
So, for example, if you did a
search for dog parks, many search engines
would give you results for all the dogs parks nearby even though you didn't type in your location.
Modern search engines also understand
more than just the words on a page, but what they actually mean in order to find
the best one that matches what you're
looking for.
For example, if you search for a "fast pitcher" it will know you're looking for an athlete, but if you search
for "large pitcher" it will find you options for you kitchen.
To understand the words better, we use something called machine learning, a type of artificial intelligence.
It enables search algorithms
to search not just individual letters or
words in the page, but understand the
underlying meaning of the words.
The internet is growing exponentially, but if the
teams that design search engines do our
jobs right, the information you want should
always be just a few keystrokes away.