Hi, my name is Jenny Martin and I'm the
director of cybersecurity investigations at Symantec.
Today cybercrime causes huge problems for society
personally, financially, and even
in matters of national security.
Just in the last few years, hundreds of millions of credit card numbers have been stolen,
tens of millions of Social Security
numbers and healthcare records were compromised,
even nuclear centrifuges
that have been hacked,
and unmanned aerial drones have been hijacked.
This is all done by exploiting vulnerabilities
in hardware and software or more often
by taking advantage of unintentional
decisions made by the people using the software.
The people committing these cyber crimes
don't fit a single profile or motivation.
It could be anyone from an international terrorist to a teenager competing for bragging rights.
Today the largest countries not only have a regular army
but also have a well armed cyber army.
In fact, the next World War may not be
fought with traditional weapons, but with
computers used to shut down national
water supplies, energy grids, and
transportation systems.
Hi my name is Parisa and
I'm Google's Security Princess.
I've worked on a lot of different Google products
in a lot of different ways to try and
make our software as secure as possible.
Now let's take a look at how cybercrime
works under the hood.
We'll learn about software viruses,
denial-of-service attacks, and phishing scams.
In biology and life, a virus is an
organism that is spread by coughing,
sneezing, or physical contact.
Viruses work by infecting cells,
injecting their genetic material, and
using those cells to replicate. They can make people really sick and then spread to other people.
A computer virus works bit similarly. A
virus is an executable program that gets
installed, usually unintentionally,
and harms the user and their computer.
It's also possible for a virus to spread itself to other
computers.
Now how does a virus get on your
computer in the first place?
There are a couple ways an attacker can
infect someone's computer.
They might lure a victim into
installing a program with deception about the
program's purpose, so for example a lot
of viruses are disguised as security updates.
It's also possible that the software on your computer has a vulnerability, so an attacker can install itself
without even needing explicit permission.
Once a virus is on your computer it can
steal or delete any of your files,
control other programs, or even allow
someone else to remotely control your computer.
Using computer viruses, hackers can take
over millions of computers world wide
and then use them as a digital army, otherwise known as a botnet, to attack and take down websites.
This kind of attack is called a
distributed denial of service.
A denial of service is when hackers
overwhelm a website with too many requests.
We call it a distributed denial-of-service when the attack comes from many computers all at once.
Most websites are ready to respond to
millions of requests a day, but if you
hit them with billions or trillions of requests,
coming from different places,
the computers are overloaded and stop
responding.
Another trick used by cybercriminals is to send large amounts of spam email in an attempt to trick people
into sharing sensitive personal information.
This is called a phishing scam.
A phishing scam is when you get what seems like a
trustworthy email asking you to log
into your account, but clicking the email
takes you to a fake website.
If you log in anyway, you've been
tricked into giving your password away.
Hackers can then use your login
credentials to access your real accounts
to steal information or maybe even to
steal your money. Fortunately there are
many companies, laws, and government
organizations working to make the
internet safer, but these
efforts are not enough.
You may think when a computer system
gets hacked the problem was the security
design or the software. Ninety percent
of the time the system gets hacked
however, it's not because of the security bug, but because of a simple mistake made by a human.
It turns out there are steps we
can all take to protect ourselves.
Often your actions not only impact the
security of your own data and computer, but the
security of everyone at your school,
workplace, and home. With billions or
trillions of dollars at stake,
cybercriminals get smarter each year and
we all need to keep up.