I'm Jasmine and I'm a program
manger on the XBOX One engineering team.
One of our biggest features is called
XBOX Live. It's an online service that connects
gamers from all around the world, and we rely
on the internet to make that happen.
This is no easy task and there are a lot of things
happening behind the scenes.
The internet is totally changing how people interact and
connect. But how does it work?
How do the computers all across the world actually communicate with each other?
Let's look at web browsing.
First, you open a web browser. It's the app
you use to access the web pages.
Next, you type in the web address, or URL, which stands
for Uniform Resource Locator of the website
you want to visit like Tumblr.com.
Hi, I'm David Karp, the founder of Tumblr and we're
here today to talk about how those web browsers
we use everyday actually work.
So you've probably wondered what actually
happens when you type an address into your web browser and then hit enter.
And it really is about as crazy
as you can imagine. So in that moment your
computer starts talking to another computer,
called a server, that's usually thousands
of miles away. And in milliseconds your computer
asks that server for a website, and that server
starts to talk back to your computer in a
language called HTTP.
HTTP stands for HyperText Transfer Protocol.
You can kind of think of
it as the language that one computer uses
to ask another computer for a document.
And it's actually really pretty straightforward.
If you were to intercept the conversation
between your computer and a web server on
the internet, it's mainly made up of something
called "GET" requests. Those are really very
simply the word GET and the name of the document
that you're requesting. So if you try to log
into Tumblr and load our login page, all you're
doing is sending a GET request to Tumblr's
server that says GET /login. And that tells
Tumblr's server that you want all of the HTML
code for the Tumblr login page.
So HTML stands
for Hyper Text Markup Language and you can
think of that as the language you use to tell
a web browser how to make a page look.
If you think about something like Wikipedia,
which is really just a big simple document
and HTML is the language that you use to make
that title big and bold, to make the font
the right font, to link certain text to certain
other pages, to make some text bold, to make some
text italic, to put an image in the middle
of the page, to align the image to the right,
to align the image to the left.
The text of
a web page is included directly in the HTML,
but other parts like images or videos are
separate files with their own URLs that
need to be requested.
The browser sends separate
HTTP requests for each of these and
displays them as they arrive.
If a web page has a lot
of different images, each of them causes a separate HTTP request and the page loads slower.
Now sometimes when you browse the web, you're not just requesting pages with GET requests.
Sometimes you send information like when you
fill out a form or type a search query.
Your browser sends this information in plain text
to the web server using an HTTP POST request.
Let's say you log in to Tumblr.
Well the first thing you do is you make a POST request, that is a POST to Tumblr's login page that has
some data attached to it. It has your email
address, it has your password. That goes to
Tumblr's server. Tumblr's server figures out
that okay, you're David. It sends a web page
back to your browser that says, Success! Logged
in as David. But along with that web page,
it also attaches a little bit of invisible cookie
data that your browser sees and knows to save.
And it's really important because it's really
the only way that a website can remember who you are.
All that cookie data really is, is
an ID card for Tumblr. It's a number that
identifies you as David. And your web browser
holds on to that number and the next time
you refresh Tumblr, the next time you go to
Tumblr.com, your web browser knows to automatically
attach that ID number with the request that
it sends over to Tumblr's servers. So now
Tumblr's servers sees the request coming from
your browser, sees the ID number, and knows
"Ok, this is a request from David."
Now, the internet is completely open.
All of its connections are shared and information
is sent in plain text. This makes it possible
for hackers to snoop on any personal information
that you send over the internet. But safe
websites prevent this, by asking your web
browser to communicate on a secure channel
using something called Secure Sockets Layer
and its successor Transport Layer Security.
You can think of SSL and TLS as a layer of
security wrapped around your communications
to protect them from snooping or tampering.
SSL and TLS are active when you see the little
lock that appears in your browser address
bar, next to the HTTPS. The HTTPS protocols
ensure that your HTTP requests are secure
and protected. When a website asks your browser
to engage in a secure connection, it first
provides a digital certificate. Which is like
an official ID card proving that it's the
website it claims to be. Digital certificates
are published by certificate authorities,
which are trusted entities that verify the
identities of websites and issue certificates
for them. Just like a government can issue
IDs or passports. Now if a website tries to
start a secure connection without a properly
issued digital certificate, your browser will
warn you.
That's the basics of web browsing!
The part of the internet we see day to day.
To summarize, HTTP and DNS manage the sending
and receiving of HTML, media files, or anything
on the web. What makes this possible under
the hood are TCP/IP and router networks that
break down and transport information in small packets.
Those packets themselves are made
up of binary, sequences of 1s and 0s that
are physically sent through electric wires,
fiber optic cables, and wireless networks.
Fortunately, once you've learned how one layer
of the internet works, you can rely on it
without remembering all the details. And we
can trust that all those layers will work
together to successively deliver information
at scale and with reliability.